so there is an issue people are very
sensitive about arrogance and the term
has a justly negative connotation and
the term humility has or humbleness it
has a very positive connotation and
while I was teaching I always was
concerned that the negative reputation
of arrogance and the positive reputation
of humbleness was a danger to my
students and at the same time I didn't
want to argue to them that being
arrogant was a good thing because it's
not we do we just lead dislike arrogant
people but if you have to air in one
direction or the other it makes sense to
air in the direction of arrogance and
the reason is this we all have the
capacity to do things if we look at the
things that we might be capable of doing
and we say well probably I couldn't
accomplish that one if we take the
humble approach then we will shoot low
and we will never discover what we're
actually truly capable of
if you overestimate what you might be
capable of well then you are in danger
of not reaching what you thought you
were going to accomplish but you will at
least discover the limits of your
capacity so if you have to err in one of
these directions you want to err in the
direction of overestimating what you may
be capable of rather than under
estimating it just simply so that you
discover what you can do and I've always
wondered if the value this social value
that we put on being humble was actually
a mechanism to get people to
self-sabotage in other words I don't
really you know I don't want students to
be humble what I want them to be is
accurate in assessing what they have
accomplished and what it means and in
setting their goals I want them to set
goals
hi and then maybe they surprised
themselves and they exceed them but if
they really set the goals high maybe
they don't quite achieve what they've
set out to achieve but at least they
discover what they're capable of it may
be they discover what they're really
interested in whereas if everybody in
the room is busy being humble and
advertising that you know that they're
not arrogant then we have really no idea
what those individuals could do or what
the room is capable of so essentially I
think people should stop penalizing what
sounds to them like arrogance because it
is a sort of generic stigma that
accompanies people who believe in
themselves that causes us not to find
our way out of various bottlenecks in
other words we need people to
contemplate the possibility that they
are capable of things that if they say
it out loud many will regard them as
Eric but we need people to contemplate
these things and to figure out whether
they are in fact capable of doing them
in order for us to escape our current
set of predicaments so I don't know give
people a break as they assess what they
might be capable of and for God's sake
when you're raising kids or teaching
students don't teach them to be humble
right you don't want them to be nasty
but teaching them to imagine that they
are capable of less than they are
actually capable of is educational
malpractice I've run it - in the
creative world I've run into people
often mistaking ambitiousness with
pretentiousness mm-hmm and it's weird
and in the art world because you have to
be a little pretentious and pretentious
more has to do with what you see
to be rather than what you're trying to
be and so there's this there's this
optics
you know like it's it's good to have
energy humility you know there's there's
positives to that that's good to have I
don't know if arrogance is the right
term I would use more ambition or or
like you said like hanging high well I'm
not defending areas I don't like
arrogant people any more than the next
person but I often think that those who
are dismissed as arrogant aren't really
arrogant what they are is ambitious in
some and you know there's kinds of
ambition that I really don't especially
like but somebody who is ambitious in
the sense of trying to discover what
might be possible I don't want to get in
that person's way and I also don't want
to imagine that I understand more about
their process of discovering something
new than that I understand I understand
my process to an extent but I'm inclined
to give somebody who might have
extraordinary capacity room to go about
doing what they do in some way that may
not make sense to me because I'm
interested in seeing what they can
accomplish we're all enhanced if they
accomplish something good and you know
the the irony here is that once somebody
has succeeded in demonstrating that they
have high capacity in some sense when
somebody has generated the object that
nobody else could build then we elevate
their story so it doesn't make sense for
that us to give them a hard time as
they're trying to accomplish the thing
and then as soon as they've demonstrated
that we were wrong and they were right
about their ability to do it then to
turn them into heroes at some level we
ought to give them room on the front end
and give them a break because frankly
almost all of the people whose stories
we circulate with respect to having
changed the way things function in some
positive direction almost all of those
people are weird and many of them broken
in some way that actually gave them some
particular capacity that's above and
beyond what the rest of us do so
I really I must say I have a a pet peeve
about a system that just sort of
generically encourages people to say out
loud that they don't believe in
themselves above some relatively common
level that's just that's a mistake I
want to know what you think you might
you know I want to know your wildest
idea and what your plan is for figuring
out if it's true
and if you're constantly reviewing
whether or not it would sound arrogant
to even discuss such an idea then you're
self sabotaging and I guess I guess what
I don't want to do is I don't want to
see self sabotage talk to people as a
sophistication it's not sophisticated to
self sabotage it is sophisticated to
figure out what you might be capable of
and then try and discover whether you
were you were right I think my brother
quotes I think it's Jim Watson as saying
something very close to if you are going
to attempt to accomplish something truly
new you will by definition be working on
something that you're not qualified to
work on and you know well the
qualification itself doesn't exist the
qualification itself doesn't exist and
so at some level you're giving yourself
permission and you know it's one thing
if somebody's life depends you know if
you're a surgeon and you have some
clever idea for some new way to do
something life and limb may depend on
whether your understanding is accurate
and so you have a different burden but
if you're you know if you're a scientist
and you have a kind of an out-there idea
about something that might be right that
might provide a lot of power if we can
find it and you hear in your mind people
dismissing you as arrogant that's just
that's a terribly hobbling thing to
imagine and so we ought to we ought to
give people a break and we ought to
realize that working backwards
the stories that we like about people
who accomplished things that others said
couldn't be done that those stories all
involved people who believed in
themselves in a way that if you forced
them to say it out loud
you might recoil from you know well the
Wright brothers thought they were gonna
win the battle to get to
heavier-than-air flight and they did and
I mean I love the Wright brothers story
because hey we know so much about what
they did and B you know it's it's
interesting that they were brothers and
you know we we have a lot of documentary
evidence of how they overcame all of the
obstacles along the way but at some
level they got very comfortable with the
idea that they were gonna beat a problem
that had stymied so many other people
and we rightly Harold them for it but
you can imagine contemporaries if you
didn't know whether the Wright brothers
were going to succeed or fail you could
imagine that they were just arrogant
guys who for some reason thought that
they were going to take to the skies
like birds you know and that that was
that was hubris and it's not is there is
there some benefit to having that social
resistance as somebody who's creative or
s but again created in the broadest
sense somebody who's chasing down
possibilities is there some sort of
positive to be gotten from the ridicule
that one receives or with us being
considered a kook or arrogant or
anything
that's a good question I think there are
a couple things going on there are
circumstances maybe within a tight-knit
group of people who are trying to
accomplish something together some
individual might try to gain more
control over the project than was
warranted by their relative capacities
or something like that in which case
their arrogance would be
counterproductive and so it might be the
best where the penalty was generated was
that there are certain contexts in which
it is not a question of an individual
assessing their own capacity it's the
individual over assessing their capacity
relative to other people in the same in
the same project who might be given the
resources so in other words it could be
a competitive modality rather than a
question of what you really believe you
yourself are capable of it could be
you're claiming capacity that you don't
really have when somebody else might
have that capacity and they will be
denied the resources because because of
your your arrogance and so it might be
that and it also might be that it
creates a kind of it might fuel certain
kinds of folks in other words being told
that you're over assessing what you're
capable of
you know does get under your skin a
little bit and you kind of feel like
I'll shut that so anyway I don't I don't
know if that's where it comes from but
it's certainly well in a world where
people who have done things that make
their names famous eventually are often
people who have imagined that they could
do what others could not do it might not
be surprising to find that the
accusation has less impact on those
folks than it does a lot of folks so
humility becomes a negative and
arrogance a positive when an individual
is facing
but then humility becomes positive and
arrogance and negative when when a group
is working together like that's where
the the value kind of shifts easing
probably I mean I again I should be
really clear I'm not defending arrogance
I really don't like arrogant people but
I will imagine that arrogance is what's
going on in somebody's case only when
there's good evidence that they're
really
overestimating what they're capable of
in a way that they should be aware of if
we're talking about some realm that I
don't know anything about and somebody
argues that they may be able to
accomplish something that sounds a
little far-fetched to me I'm not really
in a good position to assess whether
they are deluding themselves or whether
they are accurately shooting for
something that I should as a spectator
be hoping that they can accomplish and I
don't want to penalize them based on the
fact that most of the time when somebody
makes a fantastic claim they're probably
wrong because I mean I think it's like
this most of the time a an extraordinary
claim is likely to be incorrect but all
of the claims that matter started out as
extraordinary claim so all of the
important stuff is in that set in which
most of the stuff is garbage he in one
way or another but it's a fool who goes
around punishing the whole set because
99% of what's in it is garbage if a
hundred percent of what's awesome is
also in that set because then you're
just stigmatizing the awesome just
reflexively
and that's just logically a mistake so
be outrageous and conception but be
willing to admit that most of your
outrageousness is completely outrageous
in the
well I in interacting with really
interesting ultra high capacity people I
do think it would it's fair to say that
to a person I believe they have a way of
phrasing things that allows you to know
that they spot the unlikeliness of what
they are claiming might be true at the
same time that they let you know why
they think the limit might not really be
the limit in other words they evidence
that they are not unaware of why they
are unlikely to succeed they evidence
that they are aware of it and they still
think they might succeed for some reason
that they can spell out to one degree or
another and so I guess what I would say
is if I see the evidence that the person
is aware of all of the things that I'm
aware of that make me think they are
unlikely to succeed and yet they still
think they might I'm listening
right if they evidence that they are
unaware of the difficulty you know if
let's put it this way if somebody has an
idea for a perpetual motion machine and
they do not start their argument by
explaining that they understand the
physical reason that a perpetual motion
machine should not exist then that
suggests that just a cook on the other
hand if they say well there's a lot of
free energy in the universe and I
believe I have found a mechanism that
can capture it in a way that isn't
exactly perpetual motion yet it
functions an awful lot like it
well that claim is really unlikely to be
true on the other hand they've just told
me that they understand the obstacle and
they are still thinking about it for a
reason so there's evidence
see that comes packaged with the claim
yeah it's a question of whether or not
their desire to shoot for the impossible
is motivated by naivete about why it's
impossible or by thinking that they see
a gap in the completeness of our model
and in fact you know Tesla is a great
example Tesla who was extremely
successful at bringing things many
thought impossible to fruition and yet
kind of hopeless and defending his own
cause you know he and Edison are a
wonderful comparison because Edison was
a brilliant businessman and ruthless and
died very very rich and Tesla was
properly substantially more brilliant
but died penniless because he just he
cared less about that aspect of it and
he wasn't good at defending his own
interests and so you know his wealth
that he generated ended up in
Westinghouse's pocket not his own but
but there's something to the idea of
somebody should probably catalog and
probably they have already and I just
don't know exactly where to look for it
but there's gotta be a catalogue of
things people said were impossible that
have now been accomplished and you know
they're all beautiful
anytime somebody accomplishes things
that others were sure couldn't be done
the story of how they got there is
inevitably interesting and so anyway the
last thing I want to do is shout down
the tiny number of people who actually
might be able to jump one of these
impossible gaps from the basis that you
know on the basis that everybody knows
that's impossible
so arrogance yeah I don't I don't know
it's not arrogance is the pathological
version but if you go around telling
people arrogance is bad what is arrogant
so it's overestimating what you're
capable of and then the person tries to
wield that definition they don't wield
it recognizing they're not in a good
position to assess what other people are
necessarily capable of and so arrogance
itself that's right that's right
it is a a form of generic arrogance that
we empower people with to go shout down
others who have some kind of ambition to
break some limit that nobody's broken
yet it's odd how judgments when they're
wielded they blind the wielder to that
exact judgment that they end up in the
blind spot the judgment that they're
making about everybody else well this
raises an important point so there's a a
technique that comes out of the
rationalist community called steel
Manning and steel Manning is the
opposite of straw hat straw Manning is
painting your opponent's position as
weaker than it is so that you can then
defeat it steel Manning is painting your
opponent's position as strongly as you
can in order to make sure that you are
not cheating when you defeat it so
people who are really careful thinkers
are frequently excellent and may be
always excellent at understanding the
critique as well as those who are
delivering it understand it and the the
ability to speak your opponent's
position so that they can recognize it
and that they feel good about the way it
was presented before you show why it's
wrong is very powerful it's not easy but
it's very powerful and that's something
that we should be teaching right
understand what your opponent is saying
before you show why they're wrong and
it's really the heart of a good
analytical education and that that's
what makes the judgment I guess the
three sigma you're not just using the
judgment to gain power or to be right
but to assure that everybody is right
and that's probably what's persuasive
about it's kind of you've done so much
you've sunk so much work into
understanding the other side that you've
kind of taken your own self out of the
equation almost or you've extended
yourself into the the other camp as far
as possible well it it goes to this I
still don't know quite what to make of
it but when I was confronted by the
students when they showed up in my
classroom on may 23rd of last year I
said something in that hallway history
[Laughter]
well I said something that I remember
hearing myself say it and thinking it's
odd that you would say that here it's
something I said in classrooms with some
regularity but I said that I was
interested in dialectic and not debate
yeah dialectic being the process of
discovering what's true through
argumentation rather than the attempt to
win the argument for its own sake and
that process is why steel Manning a
position makes so much sense
that the if the purpose of the argument
is that those who are participating or
watching come away enhanced by what they
know then having every position
portrayed at full strength before any
conclusion is reached is good for
everybody and so anyway hopefully steel
Manning will move from being a niche
product a niche product to being a
mainstream phenomenon sooner rather than
later because we all stand to benefit
Trump
you